Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Digital Films Collection, 1971-2018; 12 Terabytes 214 digital files
  - de Onis, Paco
    - 500 Years, 2017; 108 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeOnisPaco_500Years.mp4)
      500 YEARS tells the epic story that led Guatemala to a tipping point in their history from the genocide trial of former dictator General Rios Montt to the popular movement that toppled sitting President Otto Perez Molina. Focusing on universal themes of justice, racism, power and corruption, 500 YEARS tells the story from the perspective of the majority indigenous Mayan population, and their struggles in their country's growing fight against impunity. Produced by Pamela Yates.
    - When The Mountains Tremble, 2017; 83 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeOnisPaco_WhenTheMountainsTremble.mp4)
      When the Mountains Tremble (1982) introduced indigenous rights leader Rigoberta Menchú as the storyteller in her role to expose repression during Guatemala's brutal armed conflict. Winner of the Special Jury Award at Sundance, the film was seen worldwide and translated into 10 languages. It helped put Menchú on the world stage and 10 years later she was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize. Produced by Pamela Yates, Peter Kinoy.
  - de Onis, Paco; Shaffer, Debrah
    - Witness to War, 1985; 30 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeonisPaco_Witness to War.mp4)
      One man's journey of conscience from Vietnam to El Salvador, Witness to War is the Academy Award winning story of Dr. Charlie Clements who was a pilot in Vietnam until he refused further combat missions. Stripped of his military identity, Charlie Clements dedicated his life to non-violence and healing, ultimately tending to the wounded behind rebel lines in El Salvador. A personal testament to the enduring tragedy of war as relevant in our times as it was then, this new edition includes a soul-searching return to El Salvador with Dr. Clements. Produced by Paco de Onís.
  - de Onis, Paco; Yates, Pamela
    - State of Fear, 2005; 94 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeonisPaco_State of Fear.mp4)
      How can an open society balance demands for security with democracy? Based on the findings of the Peruvian Truth and Reconciliation Commission, State of Fear follows events in Peru, yet serves as a cautionary tale for a nation like the United States. Filmmakers Pamela Yates, Peter Kinoy, and Paco de Onis masterfully blend personal testimony, history and archival footage to tell the story of escalating violence in the Andean nation and how the fear of terror undermined their democracy, making Peru a virtual dictatorship where official corruption replaced the rule of law. Terrorist attacks by Shining Path insurgents provoked a military occupation of the countryside. Military justice replaced civil authority, widespread abuses by the Peruvian Army went unpunished, and the terrorism continued to spread. Nearly 70,000 civilians eventually died at the hands of Shining Path and the Peruvian military. Produced by Paco de Onís.
    - Granito, 2011; 82 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeonisPaco_Granito.mp4)
      Sometimes a film makes history; it doesn't just document it. So it is with "Granito: How to Nail a Dictator", the astonishing film by Pamela Yates. Part political thriller, part memoir, Yates transports us back in time through a riveting, haunting tale of genocide and returns to the present with a cast of characters joined by destiny and the quest to bring a malevolent dictator to justice. As if a watchful Maya god were weaving back together threads of a story unraveled by the passage of time, forgotten by most, our characters become integral to the overarching narrative of wrongs done and justice sought that they have pieced together, each adding their granito, their tiny grain of sand, to the epic tale. Produced by Paco de Onís.
    - Disruption, 2014; 84 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeonisPaco_Disruption.mp4)
      DISRUPTION explores a groundbreaking initiative that seeks to eradicate poverty by empowering women on government assistance programs in Colombia, Peru and Brazil to "save their way out of poverty." The film interweaves women's testimonies to the transformative power of financial education with the story of Fundación Capital (winners of the 2014 Skoll Award for Social Entrepreneurship), a group of dynamic activist-economists that believes when you invest in women you change society. As women share how economic empowerment led to their growth as local political figures, entrepreneurs, and peer-educators, we follow the team at Fundación Capital while they strive to bring their successful grassroots model to millions more women across the region, collaborating with governments and big banks in order to do so. In a time when many of the world's problems seem intractable, the stories of the characters in DISRUPTION show us how society can be transformed for the better through community-led change. Produced by Paco de Onís.
    - Rebel Citizen, 2015; 76 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0027_u, Video-file DeonisPaco_Rebel Citizen.mp4)
      Pamela Yates' latest documentary, REBEL CITIZEN takes you on a revelatory tour of two time Oscar winning cinematographer Haskell Wexler's political documentary work, letting the veteran artist and activist share his vision of how to be a citizen in the world. Created for the Cinéma du Réel festival in Paris, the film was selected for the New York Film Festival in a surprise development and had its world premiere October 6th 2015. Produced by Paco de Onís.
  - Doroshwalther, Blair
    - Out In The Night, 2014; 75 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0028_u, Video-file DoroshwaltherBlair_OutInTheNight.mp4)
      Under the neon lights in a gay-friendly neighborhood of New York City, four young African-American lesbians are violently and sexually threatened by a man on the street. They defend themselves against him and are charged and convicted in the courts and in the media as a 'Gang of Killer Lesbians'. Produced by Giovanna Chesler, Mridu Chandra, Yoruba Richen.
  - Dwyer, Alicia
    - Nine To Ninety, 2013; 29 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0029_u, Video-file DwyerAlicia_NineToNinety.mp4)
      Nine To Ninety is the love story of Phyllis and Joe Sabatini, who at age 89 and 90 live in the home of their daughter and son-in-law, where they relish time with their young granddaughter Jacqueline. But as the family struggles to make ends meet and the grandparents' health problems escalate, Phyllis becomes determined to free her daughter from the burden of caring for everyone from nine to ninety. When Phyllis makes a difficult decision to move 3,000 miles away to live with their other daughter, she faces parting from Joe, her husband of 62 years. While Joe has become resigned to his ailments, Phyllis yearns to live with agency and independence even with limited resources, and the couple's surprising choices ignite bigger conversations about how to age with dignity. Produced by Producer - Juli Vizza, Co-producer - Michael Dwyer.
  - Elliott, Alice
    - The Collector Of Bedford Street, 2005; 34 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0030_u, Video-file ElliottAlice_TheCollectorOfBedfordSt.mp4)
      The Collector of Bedford Street is an Academy Award® nominated short documentary that follows the filmmaker's 60 year old neighbor, Larry Selman, a community activist and fundraiser who has an intellectual disability. Every year, Larry collects thousands of dollars for charities while living at the poverty line. When Larry's primary caregiver becomes unable to care for him, his New York City neighborhood community rallies together to protect his independent lifestyle by establishing an adult trust fund in his behalf.
    - Body And Soul, 2008; 40 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0030_u, Video-file ElliottAlice_BodyAndSoul.mp4)
      Body & Soul: Diana & Kathy, directed by Academy Award-nominee Alice Elliott, is a look at an unusual, symbiotic relationship between two people some would call profoundly disabled. Two of the country's most remarkable advocates for people with disabilities, Diana Braun, who has Down Syndrome, and Kathy Conour, who has cerebral palsy, met three decades ago and vowed to fight to live independent lives. Told in an intimate vérité style, the film is a story of a compelling and creative friendship, as Diana and Kathy model a grand experiment in independent living.
  - Entine, Sara
    - Read Me Differently, 2009; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0031_u, Video-file EntineSara_ReadMeDifferently.mp4)
      A shock of recognition in social work school leads award-winning filmmaker Sarah Entine to explore how undiagnosed dyslexia and ADHD have impacted three generations in her family, starting with her own struggles. With surprising candor, vulnerability and even a touch of humor, Read Me Differently reveals the strain of misunderstood learning differences on family relationships. It is a unique film that will generate thoughtful discussion whether in a classroom setting, work environment or at home with family members and friends. Produced by Sarah Entine.
  - Epperlein, Karina
    - Voices From Inside, 1996; 60 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0032_u, Video-file EpperleinKarina_VoicesFromInside.mp4)
      Inside a federal women's prison a German born theater artist encourages a racially mixed circle of women to find their own voices through poetry and creative expression, and meets their children on the outside. The prisoners share their life stories and experiences of prison life. Voices from Inside shatters stereotypes about crime, criminals and race. An inspiring experiment in breaking the walls with Produced by Karina Epperlein.
  - Esaki, John
    - Yuki Shimoda: Asian American Actor, 1985; 30 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0033_u, Video-file EsakiJohn_YukiShimodaAsianAmericanActor_VC.mp4)
      Yuki Shimoda: Asian American Actor celebrates the thirty-year acting career of the late Yuki Shimoda, reflecting his achievements and career disappointments typical of the minority actor. Part of New Day's Visual Communications Collection.
  - Farinella, Samantha
    - Hunting In Wartime, 2015; 66 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0034_u, Video-file Farinella_Samantha_Hunting_in_Wartime.mp4)
      Hunting in Wartime profiles Tlingit veterans from Hoonah, Alaska who saw combat during the Vietnam War. The veterans talk about surviving trauma, relating to Vietnamese civilians, readjusting to civilian life, and serving a government that systematically oppresses native people. Their stories give an important human face to the combat soldier and show the lasting affects of war on individuals, families and communities. Produced by Samantha Farinella, Christie George, Erin Greenwell and Sonya Gray.
  - Ferrero, Pat
    - Quilts In Women's Lives, 1981; 28 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0035_u, Video-file FerreroPat_QuiltsInWomen'sLives.mp4)
      A series of first person portraits of seven quilt makers, including a Mennonite, a Bulgarian immigrant, an African American, and two mid Western sisters. They provide insights into the inspiration for their work and reveal their passion and love for an art form that reflects their values and philosophy of life. Produced by Pat Ferrero.
    - Hopi Songs Of The Fourth World, 1983; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0035_u, Video-file FerreroPat_HopiSongsOfTheFourthWorld.mp4)
      Hopi: Songs of the Fourth World is a compelling study of the Hopi that captures their deep spirituality and reveals their integration of art and daily life. Amidst the beautiful images of Hopi land and life, a variety of Hopi--a farmer, religious elder, grandmother, painter, potter and weaver--speak about the preservation of the Hopi way. Produced by Producer Pat Ferrero, Associate Producer Pat Burke.
    - Hearts And Hands, 1988; 60 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0035_u, Video-file FerreroPat_HeartsAndHands.mp4)
      The film chronicles the lives of ordinary women as well as individuals such as Harriet Tubman, Elizabeth Keckley, Frances Willard and Abigail Scott Duniway through the great 19th century events: industrialization, abolition, the Civil War, westward movement, temperance and suffrage. For nineteenth century women, quilts were the podium, the pulpit and the judges' gavel, which their society denied them. Their quilts speak the language of abolition, patriotism, politics, social justice and westward expansion. Produced by Producer Pat Ferrero, Associate Producer Julie Silber.
  - Fishel, Deirdre
    - Still Doing It, 2004; 54 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0036_u, Video-file FishelDeirdre_StillDoingIt.mp4)
      Flying in the face of this culture's extreme ageism, Still Doing It explores the lives of older women. Partnered, single, straight, gay, black and white; nine extraordinary women, age 67-87, express with startling honesty and humor how they feel about themselves, sex and love in later life and the poignant realities of aging. Outspoken for their generation, these women mark a sea change. Women over 65 have been the fastest growing part of the population for decades, but with boomers turning 65, the number of older women is skyrocketing. Still Doing It looks at this society's complex relationship to women and aging with surprising and revelatory results.
    - The Boy Game, 2012; 16 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0036_u, Video-file FishelDeirdre_TheBoyGame.mp4)
      The Boy Game tackles bullying among boys at its core:the culture of toughness and silence boys live by. Targets need to be protected, absolutely, but rather than vilify bullies, The Boy Game looks to unpack the the complex dynamics that lead some boys to bully and the majority to stand watching in silent conflict.Michael Kimmel, Pulitzer Prize nominated author of Manhood in Americasays, "If the conversation about bullying is going to advance this is the project that will help us advance it."
    - Sperm Donor X, 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0036_u, Video-file FishelDeirdre_SpermDonorX.mp4)
      It's not like most little girls think "oh I can't wait to grow up and pick my sperm over the Internet." But the truth is right now only 6% of American children will grow up in a "traditional family" and we're lucky to have some of the best reproductive options worldwide. Director Deirdre Fishel takes an intimate, behind the scenes look at her own experiences and that of three other diverse women as they go on a trip they never imagined--to try to have children solo using donor sperm.
  - Frankenstein, Ellen
    - Tracing Roots, 2014; 35 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0037_u, Video-file FrankensteinEllen_TracingRoots.mp4)
      A heartfelt glimpse into the world of Haida elder and weaver, Delores Churchill and a discussion generating documentary about the multilayered meaning of an object.
  - Frick, Ellen
    - Another Side Of Peace, 2004; 60 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0038_u, Video-file FrickEllen_AnotherSideOfPeace.mp4)
      Roni Hirshenzon is a 60-year-old Israeli man who has suffered as much as any parent can imagine. Both of his sons are dead. Each died at the age of 19 as a direct result of the conflict in the region. Putting hatred and anger aside, Roni co-founded the Parents Circle, a support group for bereaved families, Israelis and Palestinians together. Another Side of Peace follows Roni's efforts to reach reconciliation and to come to terms with the deaths of his sons. He works with his Palestinian partners to connect with other bereaved families in Israel and the Palestinian Territories. Their message is simple: No More Death. Another Side of Peace provides a provocative and intimate look at the human side of the conflict, and the healing power of communication and reconciliation. This story reminds us that humanity can supersede politics.
    - Patriot Guard Riders, 2011; 73 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0038_u, Video-file FrickEllen_PatriotGuardRiders.mp4)
      Patriot Guard Riders takes us on a solemn ride to funerals of soldiers killed in action. Our guides are a 250,000-strong motorcycle group that formed to protect grieving families from harassment by a hate group. The riders escort fallen soldiers from airfield to grave, and form a protective shield of honor and respect. Soldiers are dying and families are suffering. The film reveals an unlikely but powerful bond between the riders, the grieving families and the military. Their stories chronicle a new kind of patriotism in America, where we honor the troops even if we don't believe in the war.
  - Friedman, Bonnie
    - Chrisand Bernie, 1974; 25 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0039_u, Video-file FriedmanBonnie_ChrisandBernie.mp4)
      Chris and Bernie is an intimate portrait of two 25 year old women, both working and divorced with young children.
    - Flashettes, 1975; 20 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0039_u, Video-file FriedmanBonnie_Flashettes.mp4)
      Focusing on their hopes and aspirations,this upbeat film movingly shows how the rigorous training helps to produce more than just muscle, but a positive self-identity and pride. A young man returns to his community after college and decides to do something about the alcoholism, drugs and teen pregnancies he sees everywhere. He starts a girls track club for ages 6-16, and instilling the spirit of "I CAN", The Flashettes becomes more than a team, but a second family, building self-confidence and self-respect for its
    - The Last To Know, 1981; 45 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0039_u, Video-file FriedmanBonnie_TheLastToKnow.mp4)
      Nearly one half of the estimated ten million alcoholics in the country are women, yet their special problems are totally ignored. Concealed by families, protected by friends and physicians, these women are kept invisible. They themselves are often The Last to Know. This extraordinary film speaks directly to these women by sensitively focusing on four intimate stories and shows how the medical community, the media and the values of society at large actually perpetuate alcoholism and prescription drug abuse in women.
  - Garrison, Andrew
    - Third Ward TX, 2007; 55 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0040_u, Video-file GarrisonAndrew_THIRDWARDTX.mp4)
      Two decades ago, a step ahead of the demolition crews, African-American artists board-up two blocks of abandoned houses in inner-city Houston, painting on the boards for a guerilla art exhibit. They stay to become an internationally-recognized model for community renewal and local transformation, "Project Row Houses". This is a slice of the story of Project Row Houses and their MacArthur "Genius Award" winning creative director, Rick Lowe, as their success attracts deep-pocket developers, and threatens to destroy what has been achieved. Their creative response to this new challenge surprises many—become a developer be a champion for the neighborhood. Produced by Nancy Bless, Noland Walker, Andrew Garrison.
  - Gilomen, Jen
    - Deep Down, 2010; 58 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0041_u, Video-file GilomenJen_DeepDown.mp4)
      Beverly and Terry grew up like kin on opposite sides of a mountain ridge in eastern Kentucky. Now in their fifties, the two find themselves in the midst of a debate dividing their community and the world: who controls, consumes, and benefits from our planet's shrinking supply of natural resources? While Beverly organizes her neighbors to stop Miller Brothers Coal from advancing into her hollow, Terry considers signing away the mining rights to his backyard—a decision that could destroy both of their homes. This tale of social change examines the environmental, human, and cultural impacts of our actions. Produced by Jen Gilomen & Sally Rubin.
    - Life On The Line, 2015; 27 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0041_u, Video-file GilomenJen_LifeOnTheLine.mp4)
      Life on the Line follows a year in the life of 11-year-old Kimberly Torrez as she and her family await the visa that will allow them to return to the United States after unforeseen circumstances trap them in the border-town of Nogales, Mexico. Produced by Jen Gilomen & Sally Rubin.
  - Gold, Tami
    - Passionate Politics, 2010; 58 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0042_u, Video-file GoldTami_PassionatePolitics.mp4)
      Passionate Politics tells the story of Charlotte Bunch, from idealistic young civil rights organizer to lesbian activist, to internationally-recognized leader of a campaign to put women's rights on the global human rights agenda. Charlotte has been both a product and creator of her times: every chapter in her life is a chapter in the story of modern feminist activism, from its roots in the 1960's struggles for social justice to international campaigns against gender-based violence today.
  - Goldman, Michal
    - At Home In Utopia, 2008; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0043_u, Video-file GoldmanMichal_AtHomeInUtopia.mp4)
      They wanted to change the American dream. At Home in Utopia is the story of three decades, two generations, and one cooperative apartment house built in the 1920s by immigrants, factory workers and Communists.
  - Goldsmith, Rick
    - Most Dangerous Man, 1996; 111 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0044_u, Video-file GoldsmithRick_MostDangerousMan.mp4)
      Narrated by Susan Sarandon. Seldes's written words read by Edward Asner. The Academy-Award-nominated Tell The Truth and Run, is the dramatic story of muckraking journalist George Seldes, and a piercing look at censorship and suppression in America's news media. Produced by Rick Goldsmith.
    - Tell The Truth and Run, 2010; 94 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0044_u, Video-file GoldsmithRick_TellTheTruthandRun.mp4)
      In 1971, Daniel Ellsberg, a high-level Pentagon official and Vietnam War strategist, concludes that the war is based on decades of lies and leaks 7,000 pages of top secret documents to The New York Times, making headlines around the world.The Most Dangerous Man in America is a riveting story of how one man's profound change of heart created a landmark struggle involving America's newspapers, president and Supreme Court-- a political thriller whose events led directly to Watergate, Nixon's resignation and the end of the Vietnam War. Produced by Rick Goldsmith, Judith Ehrlich.
    - Mind Game, 2015; 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0044_u, Video-file GoldsmithRick_MindGame.mp4)
      Mind/Game's portrait of "the female Michael Jordan," from troubled family life to basketball superstardom, reveals a long-hidden battle with mental illness. But even as Holdsclaw begins to embrace her emotional challenges and emerge as an outspoken mental health advocate, she encounters new obstacles to her own recovery. Narrated by Glenn Close. Produced by Rick Goldsmith.
  - Goldsmith, Rick; Ginzberg, Abby
    - Everyday Heroes, 2001; 120 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0044_u, Video-file GoldsmithRick_EverydayHeroes_2hr.mp4)